okay okay let's see I had made a
prediction that there would be 15 people
in class 4 8 9 10 11 12 13 14 off by one
pretty close Okay including myself is 15
no no no that is 15 okay so okay good
see this is what Professor is supposed
to be good at
estimation okay so uh so today today's
lecture is uh is on uh learning
manipulation so we are this is the
second last lecture the next one will be
on language models and uh I this lecture
I want to be very interactive okay
because I think what uh We've covered
the basics in the class this is more
about current work all the papers I'll
talk about are 2024 papers so so we uh
it's really meant to be an open
discussion
okay so uh what I want to start with is
what's the big picture right now in how
people are thinking about developing
policies for manipulation there are two
big approaches there are supervised
learning and there's reinforcement
learning and everything is a combination
of the two in some form or the other so
uh what is the dominant Paradigm if you
if you look at the popular press and if
you look at the company it's supervised
learning and somebody sent me a link to
an article in the New York which was
talking about the the Google uh effort
in robotics and that is all in the
supervised learning Paradigm uh I'm not
quite convinced I think actually
multiple approaches are needed and uh
the current supervised learning Paradigm
is not the final answer but uh this is a
very debatable topic and I hope we'll
have the debate during this lecture but
first I want to set the stage by talking
about the dominant Paradigm which is
which is a supervised learning Paradigm
and essentially in this Paradigm you
collect a whole bunch of demonstration
by
teleoperation and then you train a
diffusion policy on top that's the very
very short summary of what the leading
Paradigm let's get a bit into it and uh
I'll uh take you through this so first
of all uh that there are a number of
different Hardware solutions that people
have proposed for for collecting
teleoperated teleoperation data for
manipulation and uh here is one this is
called Aloha which became mobile Aloha
then there is something called Aloha 2
maybe there's an Aloha 3 yeah huh aloha
Le that's the one from Google okay so
aloha X okay so uh so I have a this this
paper is I think I think this is
probably called Aloha 2 this
one no no no this is this is a later one
this is not the first Aloha this is a
late slightly later one I think but uh
uh the one at RSS
20123 uh okay I mean there are archive
paper there are conference version so
I'm not going to get into the the
archaeology of this so uh so this is uh
this is the setup so the setup as you
can see is B manual there is a uh the
the configuration is that uh it's it's
sometimes called puppeteering so uh so
one person is
manipulating uh
uh these two arms and then there's uh
there's a gripper so essentially you
have how many degree of Freedom system
14 right six degrees of freedom for the
arm and the seventh degree is the the
gripper and 7 * 2 is 14 okay uh what's
the hardware uh the the it's a parallel
geographer uh and the sensing is that
there are multiple cameras there's a
camera which is the important camera is
the one at the
wrist okay so the one at the wrist which
looks very closely at the the object
when you are approaching it so it's
essentially doing uh some kind of closed
loop with vision in the loop where the
vision camera is at the at the
wrist
okay and uh so this paper which is from
RSS 2023 which is like just a year and
few months ago but it already seems like
ancient history so what they showed were
a series of uh teleoperated skills and
uh these are examples here uh threading
a zip cable tie uh slotting a battery
opening a lid manipulating tape from a
dispenser things like that okay uh and
this gives you more of the the the
hardware setup so there are is B manual
there's a wrist camera there's a top
camera and there's a front camera okay
and uh the arm which is being used used
is not a super high Precision arm so the
accuracy here they've listed the
repeatability is on the order of a
millimeter so one of the advantages of
this is that this is a relatively cheap
setup I mean me uh I mean there are
industrial robots which are much much
more uh much much more accurate in terms
of their reparability is much smaller
than a millimeter but it comes at a cost
and the point here is this is uh this is
a much cheaper setup
okay so is the is the hardware
configuration clear now this is not the
only setup for collecting data with t
operation there are many setups which
are around I won't get into them in this
lecture uh I mean from shuran song group
there's something called Umi Universal
manipulation interface there is one from
here hat that toru was uh responsible
for creating and there are many others
so ones which start from
sort of a uh arvr type devices okay and
then build out from there there are
these kinds of
configurations I'm sure there will be
many more coming up but I mean the
central aspect here is uh you you are uh
there's a human who is going to do the
task uh and uh and the the uh and and
then we'll collect trajectories and then
after collecting the trajectories we'll
train up all
and uh
essentially uh there are two ways so
that's a supervised learning framing of
the problem right you collect
trajectories so in computer vision in
the good old days what did we do we had
lots of images and then we said tiger
zebra horse Etc or other versions of
supervision was marking the boundaries
of an object so this is uh the same
thing in a robotics context except I
think that this job is a more painful
job for an operator
I think the computer vision job of
looking at an image and saying tiger
zebra is probably a more more fun job I
think
anyway uh this is this is more uh
tedious I think people who do this they
get tired after a little while that's
fine okay so now you collect these
trajectories now how do you build a
model what you're trying to build is a
model which says given a certain
observation and the observation here
would come from these RIS cameras plus
pro reception you're trying to predict
the action right action will be in a
usual setting of joint angles or the
Delta of the joint angles I mean that's
the uh we I won't go into those kinds of
details
here okay uh how do you take the
trajectories that you collect like this
and the typical number is in the
thousands so the Aloha Unleashed paper
from Google they have like uh 27,000
trajectories or something of that order
and uh the work from physical
intelligence which is the the company
with Serge and Chelsea I mean they have
a model which they call Pi zero and
that's based on a large number of
trajectories that they have collected so
you can imagine the game thousands go to
10 thousands which go to 100 thousands
which go to million whatever and uh yeah
uh how do I how do I use the
trajectories to train a model
uh the the this paper uses what's called
an act action condition
Transformer and uh the at the same time
I think from the shuran song and the TR
group there was diffusion policy so
these were I think two competing
approaches which came out about the same
time uh I think the diffusion policy has
won out so it seems the the the later
works are just going going for diffusion
policy both cases what are we after what
we are after is that we need a a way to
uh we need a generative model because we
want and we want a multimodal policy
multimodal not in the sense of
multisensory but modes as in statistics
you know if you have to go there's an
obstacle in the middle you can go on the
left you can go on the right but if you
go on the average you are in trouble
right so diffusion policies are
are have people are converging to that
as the standard for for doing this and I
talked about that in a previous lecture
so I won't go into more details here
okay uh these are these are this is from
their this RSS 2023 paper and this is
about saying that humans are able to do
this this task under
teleoperation so uh so precise tasks
like pick credit card open zip lock
thread zip tie uh turn pages of a book
so they're doing this all with a
parallel jog Grier and in my view that
is heroic and it's great that you can do
it but it's a little bit like showing
that a dog can ride a bicycle it's great
but uh you know uh I'm my reaction to
this is what I said in the in in my talk
at Coral which is that uh God did not
invent us with parallel geographers okay
we have multi-fingered hands and we
should use them and sooner or later
robotics should do the same so parallel
jog rippers the fact that you can do it
with parallel jog grippers is very
heroic and I Pat you on the back for it
but uh I do not see this as the right
solution 5 years from now or 10 years
from now okay it may be the right
solution now because this technology of
parallel J grippers is much better
developed in fact why go for parallel
jog grippers let's go for suction
grippers which are even simpler and work
quite well for picking up objects but my
personal opinion is the the future
researches with multifingered hand with
tactile
sensing okay but uh I mean to grant them
uh the the perspective from this line of
work is hey we can do all these things
with parallel
geographers and and they show it okay
the question is whether it will uh what
level of accuracy will this attain
so okay now I turn to the more recent
works so these are this was presented at
Coral so this is from the Google group
it's called Aloha Unleashed and uh I
think the other effort you should
consider is the one from uh from uh
physical intelligence the PI work and uh
both of these uh they have great
websites and great demos so I will give
you a flavor of this but but you should
check it out on your own so uh What uh
so so let's talk about the Google work
so the first thing they did was that
initially all the trajectories were
being collected by research scientist or
student interns or whatever and that's
at some point not a scalable solution so
now they they hired people who came and
did the trajectory collection so uh I
mean this is this is how it goes I mean
this is how it went in computer vision
too like the first round of uh in
annotations like in that data set like
Pascal was done by grad students and
postto sitting in an office okay in our
Berkeley version which was bsts which
was even earlier we had undergrads
coming over the summer to do it but uh
eventually what you need to do is you
need to pay people and Outsource the job
and that's how it went for computer
vision I would imagine this is the
future for robotics if this is the way
to
success okay uh let's see what their uh
tasks are uh I think I'm going to try to
play the video in a second but uh they
picked fairly complicated tasks so one
is uh robot finger replacement second is
hanging a shirt on a hanger third is
inserting gears so these are actually
three gears that have to be inserted
tying a
shoelace and then kitchen stacking well
this is a kind of fake kitchen but they
have to put some bowls together and put
some uh The Knife and Fork into the cup
and things like that
okay uh big picture there's going to be
a you're going to have lots of
demonstrations collected by from uh
workers and then you'll take those
trajectories put them into a
diffusion uh uh framework and and train
it uh okay here is more details on the
task shirt hanging and then they call it
shirt two versions shirt easy shirt
messy where uh basically is the shirt
pressed put in a clean formic framework
first or in a messy framework shoelace
tying again they have shoeless lace easy
lace messy robot finger replacement gear
insertion random kitchen stack I think
we'll watch movie a movie later so we'll
see
that uh shirt episode so this is what's
going on so the the we Again the video
is more compelling so you start from an
initial State you uh you kind of push
the shirt into a standard configuration
you pick up a hanger you insert you know
one one caller uh into the hanger then
you do the other caller and then you
hang on a rack okay similarly for other
tasks okay uh what's the architecture
architecture is pretty straightforward
right nothing no big deal uh okay using
use Transformers everybody uses
Transformers now uh the input uh they
input images the input images are from
all these different cameras so how many
cameras do we have we have like one
wrist camera on each arm there's a top
camera and there's a front camera so
those are the images and then you run
them through a
simple uh neural net so this is like
probably some reset reset or something
right something like that right yeah
okay there's a proceptive information
which is all the joint angles and that
you run through an MLP to get an
embedding so all of this is the input
for this transform encoder by the way
please correct me if I say give some
details which are wrong because I'm
going by memory and you may have read
this paper more more in detail okay then
you have this Transformer
decoder and uh and what is this doing if
you see uh our goal is really to predict
the actions but the way these models
work this diffusion models work is that
you try to predict the noise I mean okay
I mean you start you try and then of
course by subtraction you get the action
okay so that's what you are seeing here
so if you see this a0 plus epsilon0 A1
Plus Epsilon 1 so once I've predicted
Epsilon 0 Epsilon 1 and so on by
subtraction I get the actions and then
the do it in chunks for of like 50 50
times steps and then they they just do
that and then they they just it's a
little bit like the MPC style right you
you act and then you are getting
observations you act again and so on I I
mean they they so here one of the
impressive parts are how did they manage
to make it so fast so this is uh some
you
know excellent uh sort of sof software
engineering and and and so forth to to
make the make the thing R really fast
and the fast we care about because this
is a robotic task if you are very slow
uh it won't
work keep asking questions or making
comments as we go uh uh here are the
numbers okay I think the numbers are are
they're kind of they range from they're
sort of in the 70s I would call that
okay 75% 7
70% uh the shoeless task is
40% uh uh inserting the first gear so
they insert three gears in order so the
first gear insertion take is 95%
accurate so usually in these sequential
tasks by the time you are finishing the
last task the probability of success
goes down because at every stage you
make an error and it accumulates right
uh okay so so this gives you a flavor
and uh uh let me see okay I think that
this is uh this is their web page and
I'm going to uh scroll the web page
because because this way you get to see
the demos okay demo Aloha Unleashed okay
so this is the demo of the shoeless T
let's observe
it so there
SP year just to look for a
I
see I see
yeah yeah
okay
okay I mean I can keep playing this
forever but uh but so I mean essentially
everyone will have different opinions on
this right so uh I think if you talk to
Chelsea I mean she will say how amazing
this is and how this proves that we do
not need tactile sensing okay to me it's
a little bit like when I go to the
circus and I see some amazing feet I'm
impressed but I do not want to go do it
myself or make my children do this okay
I think I would rather have multiple
fingers and tactile sensing okay then
then develop the
the as I said I stand up and clap the
because you can do it but it's not
necessarily the case that I want to do
it this way right but you know let me
not editorialize too much okay okay uh
this is the robot finger replacement so
let's watch
this so they have to pull out one finger
and replace it by the by the connected
finger so they've taken out the the bad
finger and now they're putting in a new
finger
this is a delicate insertion task
insertion tasks are delicate normally
you want to have some sense of forces
and so on and and they are managing to
do this and of course these are the
successful trials but there will be
unsuccessful
ones question
yeah reason we haven't seen Fusion
policies combining both supervisor and
enforcement I heard a claim that some
iner
Reas uh no there are there are Works
where which try to combine with
reinforcement learning and uh we'll come
to that yeah I mean there's no inherent
reason why this cannot be done okay I I
think I I I will talk a little bit later
about I'll talk about some other
projects I mean this is all work in
progress so your idea is as good as
anyone else's in terms of what to do in
the future
I mean this group has made a very strong
commitment to supervise learning all the
way I personally don't buy that but
right now I'm presenting their point of
view with
commentary
okay and yeah and then they also believe
in parallel geographers right and no and
no
touch no
tactile okay now we get to the okay so
you you had enough of this example let
me show you the shirt hanging
demo and after this we'll have a
discussion I want to have a discussion
in the class of where what do you think
it could do or couldn't do so we should
give the pluses and minuses of this
approach so I want that to be a class
discussion but for the moment just
observe
the the demos
I I think these are Loops so I'll uh let
me go up
okay so this is generalization instead
of a blue shirt we'll do a red
shirt I'm not making this up I mean this
is actually listed as an example of
generalization simar to Intelligence
show how they were collecting data for
folding shirts and then for
generalization
they yeah
does that mean the
only
yeah yeah
this is probably called messy shirt or
something
okay unseen
shirt okay uh gear insertion so I I kind
of like this problem because I like
these insertion tasks and later on we'll
talk a little bit about the Nvidia work
on this which I think I mean they've
taken this assembly kind of problem
quite seriously and I like it because
this one uh nominal the general
classical belief in in robotics is that
this way you want some kind of force
sensing and here they're doing it
without Force sensing with these fairly
crappy grippers so you have to give them
some credit for that but as you can see
the so they'll put the first gear then
they'll try to put the second gear and
notice that uh it has it may not exactly
align so they may have to do a little
bit of
shaking okay so how how is that skill
acquired so essentially they're relying
on the human operators who are trying to
do this task they will try to do a
little bit of this and that way it will
show up in the policy so that that
slight jiggling idea is coming from the
human operators trying to do this
task which is fine I mean I think that
that's okay right I mean we have a lot
of stuff in our current AI models which
is based on getting humans to to teach
the
model okay it's looping now so I think
here the the the by the time you put the
third gear the probability of success
has dropped off but that's to be
expected in any
approach okay now this is the kitchen
task so the kitchen task let's see
what's the kitchen task so I mean these
are videos and the loops wait a bit and
you'll see the starting configuration
okay starting position so they put a cup
in
so that's a success right so this is
Tiding a
kitchen okay so uh I think let me see I
think this is probably the last demo but
so you've got the flavor now you've got
the flavor of the technology so you uh
which is trained with teop then a
diffusion policy and you can see roughly
what what this approach can do and if I
go
to the the uh this these are the
numbers okay and uh you can look at the
the the physical intelligence version of
this I mean on their website I have some
slides on that but same flavor similar
technology same flavor so let's let's
now uh let's use the next uh I think I
want to use the rest of this are
basically for a discussion of what to
expect with this Paradigm so and the
second lecture is going to be more where
reinforcement learning is used so in my
mind these are the two paradigms so now
we are focusing on the supervised
learning part so uh what are the key
questions that I ask whenever I mean in
fact in robotics uh what when we have
the interaction between Robotics and
machine learning what are the questions
we should ask there there are two right
and generalization
and the second is
robustness so what do I mean by
generalization generalization means that
it should generalize across different
objects objects of different size shape
appearance and so on it should
generalize across different tables and
surfaces it should generalize across
different camera viewpoints and so on so
generalization uh in the setting of P
recognition means like I have to
recognize the dog in spite of the fact
that it can be a different breed of dog
different pose of dog different lighting
under occlusion Etc so generalization
should mean that I mean we should not
change the meaning of the word
generalization it it is still that
meaning what does robustness
mean robustness has to do with the fact
robustness is not what we consider in
pattern recognition it but it's
something we consider in contr so when
we are performing a task things will go
wrong life is like that something will
go slightly wrong and can you manage to
recover from that okay so robustness in
this setting is really just controll uh
when you have feedback control it's all
designed for things will go slightly
wrong and we need
to fix that we need to correct for that
we need to compensate for that so so we
can uh we want that so if both of these
attri so the the both if both of these
attributes are what we care about and we
have to judge uh any Paradigm I mean
this Paradigm reinforcement learning
Paradigm whatever on
this third second order are concerns
like is it easy to do is it convenient
and so on I mean those are also valid
concerns uh uh but but but these are the
most important criteria for evaluating
an
and so I for robustness you could say in
a way this is these are the numbers
which tell you a little bit so what what
would be our main question here the main
question here is uh scaling Behavior so
their claim this is what you get with
like 8,000 so you get this success rate
of 70% at with
8,658 uh uh
demonstrations uh what happens if you
have 15,000 what happens if you have
30,000 what happens with when you have
100,000 so so we we have to ask the
question about what are the scaling
laws right and I I don't think that this
question is settled yet I mean we can
have our intuitions and discuss it but
the the I think the underlying thesis of
this line of work is that uh that there
are scaling laws here just the way they
existed for computer vision tasks or
llms and there will be similar scaling
laws and that in a tractable amount of
time right like if it requires one
trillion demonstrations you're not
getting there right so the question is
will uh will getting to a million
demonstrations be okay how much will it
cost in time and money is it affordable
I mean I think these are fair questions
which my my expectation is that we will
get the answer to this I mean now the
number of people exploring these
approaches so in a year or 6 months or
two month two years you will get you'll
start to see the answer to these
questions my second uh so that's that's
one dimension so I I'm converting this
to scaling
laws and scaling has worked in other
settings with machine learning we don't
know how well it will work here
generalization what is generalization
so here is where I have my biggest
concerns the the the techniques
are they the what is doing a lot of the
heavy lifting is that that uh that wrist
camera and the appearance is is very
specific so the question is uh how well
will the approaches
generalized across different objects so
in fact in I think in some of the paper
uh I think one of the papers maybe it
was from shuran songs group where there
is a discussion of what they call narrow
generalization versus broad
generalization so narrow generalization
is at that same site so so let's say at
Google they've got this platform uh
where they're doing all this work right
but this is something which is in at
Google right and and they they probably
set up multiple versions of this so that
different uh tele operators could be
used to collect trajectories now my home
where I fold my laundry doesn't look
anything like this
right uh and and neither does your home
or anyone else's home so the
generalization has to work for different
object types for different homes for XYZ
right uh the question here is will this
will this
work okay and then it again gets tied
back to the scaling question will it
scale uh will scaling is scaling the
answer to everything so if scaling is
the answer to everything scaling will
deal with generalization and scaling
will deal with robustness so the error
rate comes down so we Happy on the
robustness the Gen it works for many
different kinds of
objects uh that is the generalization
question okay so I think I've spoken
enough uh let me just uh show you the
the version from uh physical
intelligence so this is our first
generalist policy very catchy name Pi Z
and uh what do they show so they show
things like this okay so they have
basically they pull some clothes out of
a washing
machine they are
folding uh let's
see uh what is is more demos
here I mean there's some other stuff
about using different robot embodiment
but to me that's not the central issue
the central issue is uh you know I mean
if if you can't do the task well with
one robot then you're not going to do it
better with eight
robots
right so this is uh one of their
examples folding a cardboard box uh
okay let's see
uh
uh okay I yeah let's let's go
for uh so they have kind of these Demos
in more slightly more quote open world
settings but uh let's let's do a
discussion here I I'd like people to
express their points of view or
whichever you can you know what you like
what you don't like what you're betting
is we should take down everyone's
predictions and we can check back in two
years from now you
know okay anyone wants to speak
up just speak loudly because that way we
can uh it's definitely good that is
deployed in a homelike
environment and you know you can take
out clothes put them in the dryer so
maybe we're getting closer to seeing
robots deployed in the home this are Tas
when you tell people about robots
getting more advanced they think about
stuff like this yeah can I have it at
home helping washing or cooking
mhm I think it's a good start that they
attempted the task yeah no no that that
I agree I I want to say that uh I mean
in the the most of the classical
robotics work is for the factory floor
or the warehouse floor and here we are
going for the home and which I believe
is is interesting and important right
and we are all after this goal of the
home robot so so that I agree with I I
want to give a state one more thing
which I like which is that
is just that the the range of tasks that
are studied is being expanded that's a
good thing okay in fact uh in one of my
earlier lectures I had this set of
common Atomic skills mainly because I'm
trying to push that robotics is more
than pick and place so I think them
trying out all these tasks is great I
think uh what the
interesting uh one interesting thing
which comes from that is just specifying
the task is hard so for me as a human to
tell the computer to do this task how do
I do that that is a challenge it's
really a challenge particularly for
reinforcement learning approaches
because it has to be done by reward
shaping whereas uh demonstrating a
task either with a human just doing it
and a camera observing or through this
teleop these are very natural ways to
specify a task so so this is this is an
aspect of the solution it's not unique
to them but uh but I like
this I think the my concerns are to do
with these two questions generalization
robustness and what will be the scaling
Behavior but I I want to hear other
people's opinions not mine yeah feel
like in robotics